howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is journalist and author
Steven Levy hi Jim
Steven great to have you here somebody
whose career I have been following since
long long ago steven has been following
the personal computer and online world
since damn near the beginning the first
book of his which I read was hackers
heroes of the computer revolution from
1984 when hackers was still mostly a
positive term indeed that book as far as
I can tell was the catalyst for the
legendary hackers conference of 1984
quite a who's-who for the early days of
computing and networks
he also wrote in the Plex how Google
thinks works and shapes our lives which
I also read and it was very prescient to
my mind about the culture and power of
Google I made my own first visit to the
Plex in early 2014 and it was stunningly
like how Stephen had drawn it it was
like wow okay it's like I had been here
before
came from that book in addition to his
influential books Stephen is a longtime
top technology journalist he's currently
Wired's editor at large and has appeared
in Rolling Stone Harper's Magazine
Macworld the New York Times Magazine
Esquire The New Yorker and many more
today we're mostly going to talk about
Stephens new book Facebook as always
links are available to Stephens book and
two references organizations and
articles that we reference in this
discussion let's start with the
unprecedent level and duration of the
access you had to Facebook and to
Jacques and his management team did you
tell us a little bit about how it came
to be and kind of how the relationship
grew and changed over what period of
time
sure so I wanted to write this book
beginning I think in 2015 I I could
pinpoint the date I think was August
27th 2015
when Zuckerberg posted a billion people
were online in the previous 24 hours on
Facebook and that had never happened
before you get a billion people for the
World Cup that's people just watching
something there are members of anything
they can't talk to each other and this
wasn't a spike this was a baseline
Facebook was only going to grow I've
been covering Facebook for a number of
years beginning when it was just the
college network and it struck me that
Zuckerberg very ambitious plans were on
the way to being fulfilled and I wanted
to document that and the way I do that
you mentioned the Google book is to dive
in there and learn everything I can
about this so you know if I were doing a
book without cooperation from Facebook I
talked to a lot of people outside the
company I try to talk to people inside
the company away from the campus and you
know people have opinions about it so I
did a lot of stuff that you do when you
don't place doesn't cooperate but I
talked them into cooperating with me on
the record officially um you know kind
of in exchange they didn't get anything
from me I didn't show them the book till
after was printed all the trees were
dead and it was too late to do anything
about it so that was just a pure gain
for me and I told them then someone has
to do this someone has to document this
historical ascent of this company even
if it isn't me it should be someone but
it should be me and they knew who I was
from my track record and I've been
covering Facebook and they knew me to be
trustworthy they knew going in there
that there would probably be stuff in
there that they didn't like they didn't
anticipate that a few months after I
started writing the book Facebook would
be thrust into a trajectory that put it
in crisis and exposed a lot of their
misdeeds which of course I documented in
detail but
I kept my implicit promise to be fair
and delivered a book which I think tells
the story of Facebook Wow and as far as
I know nobody else has ever had this
level of access I've read some other
books about Facebook and articles and
they don't have the sense of I was there
like this one does yeah particularly
when you try to get to know an enigmatic
character like Zuckerberg he doesn't
trust people very easily so it really
takes a long time for him to be candid
with someone and remarkably the best two
interviews I wound up doing with him
ever were the last two interviews I did
in the book when I was already writing
the book this is in 2019 where I was
able to ask him questions that normally
he would walk out of the room if he got
from someone but he knew because I knew
the company so well that he had to
grapple with it and he had to give me
the answers as much for himself as to me
very good we will kind of weave through
this to the grid that I can you know
your insights into the nature of
Zuckerberg and he's obviously a world
historical person and I suspect you have
as much insight on him as anybody who
isn't his family let's start with in the
book early on you dig into Zuckerberg
denial of the impact that Facebook may
be either had or didn't have in 2016
elections from the flow of
misinformation in fact he calls it a
crazy idea at that time you know in some
sense it's the book unfolds that seems
to be a pivotal moment when Zuckerberg
view or at least his public
pronouncement about the nature of
Facebook became disconnected from the
broader public perception of the impact
and perhaps the duties of Facebook you
know since then perceptions have clearly
changed as you point out investigations
on multiple content charges of breach of
fiduciary duties with respect to privacy
huge fines etc did this strike you as
the pivotal moment in the unfolding of
Facebook or at least the later days of
Facebook the election was the pivotal
moment Facebook didn't
in one day but the election exposed and
made it difficult to ignore the things
about Facebook which were worrisome
I think if Donald Trump wasn't elected
president this reckoning might not have
happened there it certainly wouldn't
have happened at this time you know as I
get into in the book there's plenty of
events where people called out Facebook
for privacy violations for being
cavalier about the content on the
network all sorts of things but they
managed to skate by it and not really
pay the price for when it went wrong it
figured he can kind of go along and
apologize for what it did wrong and
going along in its merry way but after
the election people took a closer look
at what happened on Facebook than what
was happening on Facebook and became
less forgiving about it because they
realized what an impact it had now that
particular statement by Zuckerberg came
in a conference two days after the
election I was in the room when he said
it and it really didn't level the room
to say when he said it's crazy to think
that we affected the election people
were still digesting it but what I only
learned later was the day before that
there was a big meeting at Facebook
impede were in tears and they were one
day asking themselves did we have
anything to do with that so in a way he
wasn't dealing totally candidly when he
brushed it off because he knew from the
reaction of his own employees that there
was a concern about this at that point
and that same shock that the public had
after Trump got elected and they said
well what about a lot of stuff that
happened on Facebook that I've been you
do with it that was a question that was
being asked in Menlo Park and the other
Facebook offices by Facebook employees
indeed it's interesting to my mind that
that highlighted to me what I took as
sort of an implicit theme of your book
which I don't think ever quite made it
explicit which was that you know
Facebook started out in that era that
was kind of congruent with the hacker
culture you know spirit of doing
something outrageous but useful you know
the noses of the powers-that-be which
we'll talk about a little bit later how
Zuckerberg kind of got sideways with the
admin at Harvard very slowly climbed a
ramp in this hacker spirit and if we
think back you know you and I are
old-timers we go back to the earliest
days of the online world I worked at the
source which was the very first consumer
online service from 1980 to 1982 yeah I
was on this world yeah I was TC a zero
eight zero that's how early I was and
you know if we recall you know how the
evolution of the considered
responsibility of these platforms in the
80s we had services like CompuServe you
know the source I quit after two years
Reader's Digest had bought it and
stifled it and just didn't understand
what they had I up and quit and became
an entrepreneur I'm quite a successful
one using the technologies to deliver
information into professional audiences
but the consumer online world you know
took off at a fairly good pace
CompuServe by the mid-80s had millions
of users and at the time the ruling law
was a case called cubby vs. CompuServe
such as a court decision which basically
entirely let copy serve off the hook for
what happened there so long as it did
not do any moderating which is quite
interesting and that was the consensus
both of the legal framework and what we
might call you know the hacker
Sensibility which is hey these platforms
are to allow people to get together and
talk and you know the biggest thing on
CompuServe were things called SIG's
special interest groups kind of a
combination of a forum and a software
repository and some other little
features like they eventually had chat
built into him and their multi-user chat
so again CompuServe was really about
interaction they saw that way on but the
ethos at that time was not their problem
what gets said on that platform then
later 1996 after a lot of lobbying and
conversation on Capitol Hill and you
know I still remember a lot of that you
know an organization I was think member
number seven of the EF F had a role in
this as well
the famous section 230 of the
Communications Decency Act which
basically gave platforms
AOL at that time was still relatively
big and various other players
essentially immunity from what the
people on their platform said even if
they did do moderation yeah that was the
key that you know I worked for Newsweek
for twelve years I was a chief
technology writer and I remember I had
actually fairly recently gotten in
Newsweek then interviewed Al Gore the
night that passed you know I was writing
about it for Newsweek and and we and we
talked about it and that you know that
basically gave the platforms the right
to do some moderation as you point out
it was here before it was binary either
you hands-off and you weren't
responsible or if you mess with it then
they could sue you and say well yeah hey
you were moderating so you are
responsible so now they were able to say
hey we can take out things like hate
speech or you know or threats or
whatever you know to make it a safer
environment for people and still not be
responsible for vetting it like an
editor and Wired would that a story to
make sure that we don't get sued because
we are responsible for our content if we
libel someone in an article in Wired we
have to Ansel for it not if you post
something on AOL you know or later
Facebook so Facebook was a child of the
1996 communications act indeed and I
guess my point is that was the ethos of
that time yeah yeah but Facebook Mark
Zuckerberg had no consciousness of that
at all
when he started Facebook and as a
college network and I actually get into
the the moment where that started become
a factor and it wasn't the engineer is
the Zuka Berg hired or Zuckerberg
himself who became concerned about this
it was the people who answered the mail
the support people and these were people
who maybe dropped out of college were
just recently graduated from college
very early employees of Facebook who
became multimillionaires just because
they were lucky enough to walk you know
up the stairs
Facebook's office at the end 2005 or
whatever and they've got these
complaints and people saying hey here's
someone who's saying bad things
about gay people here's someone who's
posting and they could picture you know
brands porn or whatever and they realize
that Facebook had to be involved in this
and they sat around and and just made
some informal rules it was almost like a
you know an ad-hoc agreement and when
you signed on as a new employee to do
support the person next to you would you
know give you advice and saying hey what
should I do about this piece of content
so I was complaining about it they said
well there's a person wearing pants no
pants take it out you know and and for
the formal rules they eventually evolved
into what's now like a 37 page set of
community standards and then there's a
you know a whole larger body of work
which gets up more detail but that's
given to tens of thousands of content
moderators throughout the world that try
to police what is you know the world's
most active hotbed of discussion and bad
pop to you know and and and content
which is hate content content which is
harmful content where terrorists try to
put their work on there so that all came
from that from that informal discussion
there yep ban you talked about that was
I thought that was actually quite
interesting how it was essentially a
shared editable text document that
people just added into in an ad hoc
fashion kind of interesting but let's go
back a little bit to the history of this
command again there were millions of
people on CompuServe AOL even the well
didn't have millions but had you know
over ten thousand at its peak you and I
have both been a member of the well for
a long time there didn't seem to be so
much concern about so-called bad things
I mean there were some bad things on
CompuServe way back in the day and
CompuServe view on it was oh well we
don't care not our job and the source
right where I work so I was more aware
of how we did it again it was hands-off
with respect to content but because it
was owned by The Reader's Digest oddly
they were extraordinarily persnickety
about George Carlin's obscene words and
so they had you know strict rule can't
say fuck right in fact I got a big
argument and all
threaten to quit when the chairman of
the source Reader's Digest executive
demanded that I take down from user
publishing one of my earlier products a
essay written by one of our users which
he was getting paid for it sort of a
precursor of blogs a very humorous riff
on all the various ways fuck could be
used you know The Reader's Digest
wouldn't have cared if there was a
neo-nazi group on the source but they
had you know classic old-school fuss the
editorial control over the actual words
that could be used and so why did it why
does it make a difference today that we
should suppress hate speech say when it
didn't in say 1982 so this is you know
the the benefit of going back and
looking over the the history of company
how it evolved so the the reason why
that wasn't such you know an alarming
thing in the source or CompuServe or
whatever is that there was no equivalent
of going viral on those things you know
Facebook built in the tools to allow
certain kind of posts just to percolate
like and this is a horrible comparison
for time right now like a like a virus
right and you know one of the big
product initiatives actually named
pandemic of Facebook's the name one of
the chapters of my book that I wrote way
before this happened mmm
Facebook thought that was great because
Facebook was really obsessed with growth
and things like that got people on the
platform and and drew them in there and
had more time there was great for growth
and retention so when things started
going viral on Facebook which happened
because they would distribute posts they
drank them higher on your newsfeed if
more people were engaging with it as
precisely people you knew you know that
allowed things to get huge audiences of
millions and millions of people and then
businesses cropped up to take advantage
of that the Arab Spring took advantage
of that and Facebook thought that was
terrific that's fantastic and never
really seriously consider the
consequences of the destructive content
being distributed widely and going viral
on Facebook or and why
was more likely to go viral on Facebook
then content which was upstanding and
well researched so this was a
consequence that at first they didn't
think of and then was called to their
attention that they stuck their heads in
the sand and ignore it because it didn't
really fit the way they wanted the
company to grow yep actually I think
that's interesting and in fact I might
even go a step further and say they
didn't really stick their head in the
sand quite the opposite because they
were so metrics driven and the key
metric for a long time was engagement
they actually had a positive incentive
not just head-in-the-sand to tweak their
algorithms yeah they had to ignore the
idea that you know you're absolutely
right that they thought that was the
pursue their going they had to ignore
the fact that it they were encouraging
the engine that wound up becoming a very
efficient engine of destructive content
which could erode democracy for instance
and it could lead people to rot and and
caused fatal riots in countries where
Facebook didn't have anyone who spoke in
the native language yeah I wouldn't say
necessarily clearly their algorithm was
not optimised for badness but what it
was optimized for was high cognitive
impact all right you know the
sensational content that's a term that
the Zuckerberg is actually used is more
popular they measure this then non
sensational content that that's you know
we know this you know the look at like
what you put on the cover of a tabloid
newspaper but that dominates what you do
and you can no one is checking to make
sure that even truthful things are
circulated widely that's a destructive
force on society and that could help
elect wait who tell lies about their
opponents yeah
but again I'm gonna play a little bit of
a contrarian here just for fun see how
you respond you know in the previous
world prior to the networked world you
know we had scurrilous pieces of shit
like the weekly news of the world the
most outrageous and then things like the
National Enquirer which had readerships
in the millions that published blatant
lies ridiculous stuff you know Liz
Taylor has a baby with an Al
right or you know on and on and on
millions of people were reading
scurrilous shit on these publications
and many of us who were you know sort of
hardcore civil libertarians said oh well
that's the cost of free speech and so
there's a part of me from that old
hacker culture and you remember what
hackers are like you were one of the
central figures in catalyzing that the
hacker movement and you remember the
early days of online when the idea of
censorship other than again personal
attacks daxing etc would have been
rejected by the ethos of online and that
the argument was the answer for bad
speech was good speech right right are
we really sure that the feel of the need
to censor is actually net good well
here's here's the difference between the
world weekly news what what happened in
in the print world with the world weekly
news and what happens on Facebook and
it's a design issue it's not necessarily
a censorship issue it's it's how
Facebook handles it so when you got the
world weekly news and sometimes I would
you know because the teenager I'd take
the subway into into downtown
Philadelphia and you know we go to a
newsstand and we'd buy the real weekly
news we'd read about the aliens and the
you know the gruesome stuff people with
six arms or whatever and it was all the
world weekly news we knew it what it was
it did the world weekly news wasn't
mixed in with in New York Times and
other publications you know you go in
your newsfeed on Facebook and an article
from the world weekly news universe gets
mixed head-to-head with an article from
you know the New York Times or wired or
other things and sometimes is
intentionally masked to look like that
they'll make up a publication like you
know the Denver Guardian there's no
Denver Guardian it's with you know that
the address of the publication was a
parking lot in Denver but you won't be
able to tell the difference between the
Denver Guardian which is a made-up
publication and the Denver Post which is
the newspaper in Denver so that's the
difference the difference is that you
can't tell from
all the signals you get when you put
your 15 cents you know they we used to
spend the buy the world weekly news and
we knew we were going to get a romp
which maybe wasn't the most rigorous
journalism we knew that yeah but on
Facebook it's hard to tell and people
take advantage of that to circulate
content which is intended to mislead and
then the next step is and to target it
to people who are most likely to
misinterpret it or you know or be
influenced by it because of their
particular biases yeah in fact I don't
recall if you mentioned in the book I do
know from my own readings on the topic
that a goodly amount of the most clever
disinformation in the 2016 election was
actually done for profit by Eastern
European and Balkan you know the famous
Macedonian teenagers right they
discovered that you could come out with
the most outrageous shit about the 2016
election that was you know highly
inflammatory cognitive button-pushing
get lots of reads and sells some ads
right Facebook knew that you know and
they you know when they looked into it
that's what they found there was this
little one particular town in Macedonia
where a lot of people are driving very
fancy cars because they got rich by you
know taking a far-right wing blog item
totally made-up and you know the Pope
endorses Trump or whatever
Hillary killed an FBI agent and making
up a phony publication you know that it
supposedly came from and circulated
people clicked on it there were ads and
those people got paid for from the ads
as it turns out they discovered did
content which leaned towards the right
you know she made you like dislike
hillary or not won a vote or whatever
was more profitable so there was more of
that stuff on there and then of course
there was the Russian interference which
they have their own reasons for a
circulating content which favorite Trump
but you know you're right by numbers
most of it was for profit yep and it was
essentially an ecosystem again it
reminds me a lot of the famous town in I
guess village and County in Mexico where
suddenly people were driving fancy brand
new pickup trucks they weren't into
Mercedes then the road
too bad and it turned out that this
whole village was involved in building
artifacts for World War Craft you know
so when an ecosystem appears somebody
will figure out how to exploit it you
know yeah no definitely what's
interesting is when Facebook in the last
you know six weeks in the election this
really became apparent and people
started complaining about it
Barack Obama in a rally for Clinton
you know actually called out Facebook
for this and and you know Facebook I
described a meeting they had Sheryl
Sandberg was on the phone and there were
the policy people and taking the lead
with the head of Facebook's policy in
Washington DC who came from you know the
Bush administration he was best friends
with Cavanaugh people in an office told
me that he saw his job as protecting the
Republican side and he said we're not
gonna do anything about it we're not
going to take this down because you know
why offend the right of course it is
difficult right how do you do it and and
yet not remain a force for the left you
have the complaint was you're right the
complaint was oh well we don't want to
tilt the playing field but the fact was
the playing field was already tilted by
taking out that toxic content you
actually would be leveling the playing
field it was tilted not by accident but
because the way facebook was designed it
was vulnerable to being exploited in
that sense you know Mark Zuckerberg
didn't intend to say hey I won you know
uh bad content to thrive but he built it
to generate interest than the tension
and keep people on there in a way where
that was a consequence and a lot of
people called him out people not being
nothing responsibility for fixing that
when it became clear you know certainly
clear by the end of that election cycle
then it was causing damage there's
another aspect going back to electoral
advertising which makes all online
advertising different but particularly
Facebook which is micro targeting right
historically if I ran an ad and let's
say I made a grossly racist appeal I
would get a lot of comeback as a
candidate for
grossly racist ad right I remember
George HW Bush got a lot of swing back
for his Willie Horton ads right he
eventually won but he took a lot of
grief
the problem with micro-targeting is I
can send those racist ads just to
racists who aren't likely to complain
and I think that's something that the
affordances that Facebook provides to
all marketers but particularly political
marketers fundamentally changes the game
well it doesn't fundamentally change the
game you combine it with the cost
advantage because you could do micro
targeting with direct mail but it was
very expensive you can do micro
targeting on Facebook and it's really
cheap and allows you to you know send
different messages to different people
and not be held publicly accountable for
your advertising yeah yeah as you say it
doesn't change the game it advances it
and then it advances it so far that it
does change the game I was saying that
if you do the same thing at a bigger
speed and a lower cost it actually
becomes a different thing because you're
able to use it in a sentence where it
affects the situation much more than if
you did it at a lower level
that's like saying computers we use now
and our hands or different devices than
those things that we used in the early
1980s so I think you know the micro
targeting becomes a very big issue
because Facebook enables not to happen
and as you say these political marketers
can identify people who are susceptible
to messages so Facebook's model is to
deliver advertisements to people who are
likely to respond to it and they argue
Facebook argues that you should welcome
these advertisements because they are
relevant to you they are going to give
you buying opportunities up to things
that you actually want to buy if you're
a fan of an obscure music group and
there's some t-shirt then you never
would have known about with this group's
you know the logo on it it'll find you
and say you know hey here's something
that you will with article clothing you
will love to have that you didn't know
existed and I've had that happened to me
on Facebook and bought the t-shirt
but where it's different is when
Facebook understands or you know enough
about you to know where your weakness is
and then sells your contact the people
give allows people to contact you to
exploit your weakness that's something
different
people aren't so happy when they hear
they're being manipulated by people you
know people are able to know their
weaknesses and then exploit them that's
something different if different
character and we're having a debate now
about whether that's kosher to do in a
political campaign some people think
that Facebook or anyone else shouldn't
be allowed to do that degree of micro
targeting in a campaign yeah that's an
interesting question and as far as I
know Facebook is holding the line that
they're going to allow it for the coming
election and I can tell you from some of
my own sources that the Republicans
particularly the Trump campaign have
invested vast sums in running the most
sophisticated ever social media based
election campaign and have raised a
gigantic war chest and in fact part of
their pitch to donors is specifically
this so it's going to be part of the
20/20 experience you know in 2016 they
actually did run the best campaign and
by far and the people of Facebook we're
looked on in awe at how well the Trump
campaign used Facebook and I you know
come face book also lent them help they
embedded some of their employees in the
campaign just like they do for any big
advertiser to help them use the platform
better they offered the same to the
Clinton campaign the Clinton campaign
said not don't don't need it go away
you're not important you know we want to
do that but the Trump campaign took the
help and and in a way that they didn't
need it quite as much because they
really understood Facebook and we're
able to do things like do though some
days they ran a hundred seventy five
thousand different ads to different
people because they were able to tailor
them to exactly what they thought those
targets wanted right here's the person
who's interested in gun rights let's get
a gun ad to them here's a person who's
anti-abortion let's do that oh here's a
person who's an African American they're
probably going to vote for Trump let's
send them something they get them
sick of the whole system so maybe they
won't vote so they were able to do all
these different ads the people did you
know to be very effective in helping one
Election Day yep and they're gonna do it
even more this time I can tell you
though I will say one thing that has
changed I do a little bit of promoting
of my podcast on Facebook and I was
getting a fair number of my episodes
censured by the advertising clearance
engine at Facebook because some of my
episodes maybe 15% of them are sort of
political right and they now require you
to register as a political advertiser if
you're going to run political ads and
you have to put a check on the ad if you
believe that it infringes in the
political space and so I actually went
through the process of registering as a
political advertiser on Facebook and
when I have an episode that is
explicitly political I'll check the box
so unlike in 2016 Facebook knows what is
a political ad and what is not you in
2016 they didn't know or care so at
least in theory and frankly I don't know
whether they're doing this or not but
they should it would be really helpful
to shall we say the hygiene of political
discourse if facebook published every ad
that was run with the political checkbox
next to it and the micro-targeting
filter that was applied to it so that
public interests people obviously
citizens aren't gonna do it'd be too
much data but you know public interest
groups
if only the opponent could go through
this and say huh you know Biden is you
know appealing to black nationalists
with an obviously racist meme or Trump
is you know appealing to neo-nazis but
doing it in a surreptitious way that
only neo-nazis see so that one reform
alone could be quite helpful in letting
you know the immune system of discourse
in journalism and frankly even
competition identify abuse of micro
targeting well actually they do that
they do and when you could check that
box and you know you that the hot stuff
goes into an archive that in theory
could be searched um you know there's a
question about how you know great
or to search it and you know can help
what kind of access research groups have
to that archive but you know that that's
the fury that you know that anything a
protocol being able to archive and then
when they first did that media outlets
were outraged when they would do
articles about political things and and
Facebook would say well that's that's
political and said wait a minute we're
not playing we're we're news and you
know I think Jim you know it's
interesting I did see what you would
have happened if you push back and said
I'm a news source I'm not a political
source because there was a big fight
within Facebook the people who work with
journalists and Facebook in the Facebook
journalism project we're saying hey we
really can't do that and then we're
gonna get a lot of crap from journalists
and journalists and publishers and
that's what they did and Facebook did
pull back a little from that but it is
difficult to determine what's political
and what's not political when it's not a
campaign actually taking out the ad but
you know it could be like a podcast of
someone who may lean left to right but
that's okay yeah there's publications
like that or it could be a publication
like the New York Times or Wall Street
Journal or beat'em right Bart that says
you know well this is you know an
editorial we're running so it gets into
murky grounds yeah it does and frankly I
had that thought but at the tiny level I
advertised clearly I'm just being
filtered by machine and it wasn't worth
my time to go argue with the goddamn
Borg right and trying to deal with
Facebook it's impossible there's no way
to get ahold anybody it's just a fucking
nightmare so I said all right I'll go to
the process and get registered as an
advertiser but you were right probably I
could have fought the fight but it
wasn't worth the time
let's change directions here a little
bit this has been extraordinarily
interesting but I'd like to you know
sort of focus back a little bit on
Zuckerberg the person and how he evolved
both as a person and his character and
how Facebook evolved from earlier things
that he did and and kind of came up a
slope a little bit at a time
one of the things that's you know struck
me when I read the book and then went
researched it again to create my topics
for the show was
Zuckerberg was born in 1984 he's a baby
right I'd already left the source and
started my first two companies by 1984
I guess he's the king of the Millennials
which I think in itself is interesting
and something us geezers need to keep in
mind when we think about Zuckerberg that
he is if not quite an internet native
he's certainly an online native and I
think that's something well worth
keeping in mind when we think about
Zuckerberg how much did that came
through in his personality that he was
an online native quite quite a lot right
in 1984 you mentioned Huelva that's when
my first book came out and that's when
that hackers conference which was indeed
generated by my book that was my book
party
the Kevin Kelly in Stuart brand the
people whole earth through after they
did that book so he grew up as an AOL
Instant Messenger kid and he was always
building projects and thinking about
what to do he built some projects on top
of that he built a product that was very
much like based on synapse which was
it's called synapse a I it was based on
Wynn app which was the music player
which AOL bought and that was very much
his frame of mind and then and all the
stuff woman on the internet in the web
very he grew up using web-based tools
and that's why he was able to build
Facebook so quickly is because he
understood in a way that maybe an older
person wouldn't have understood then you
could build an application really
quickly and it could be really powerful
it can be updated really quickly using
some of the brand new tools of
development which had come out along
with the popularization of the web in
the late 90s and early 2000s and that
really framed the way he thought about
things to the degree that when the
mobile revolution came six seven years
later in around 2010 2011 Zuckerberg was
quite short he was like more of a web
person and his generation was a little
behind in mobile and Facebook got cut
short and had to really regain itself in
order to build itself into a mobile
company and that was in part because
Burg's mentality was the web interesting
and that reminds me a tremendous amount
as I read that in your book and I
remember the history of it and part of
the expenditure of a ridiculously large
sum of money for whatsapp was about
closing that gap it reminded me a lot of
gates Bill Gates right mr. PC he was
amazingly blind to the Internet right
right and they famously famously had to
call an all-hands meeting and refocused
the company on the internet but they did
it years late and you're very very
similar though unlike Microsoft
Zuckerberg did make the change in time I
was amazed watching their percentage go
from web-based app based just was like a
rocket ship very very rapidly now
another thing that you mentioned I
believe about a dozen times in the book
is that Jacques was a great gamer PC
based games in particular civilization
being one of his favorite games but also
risk and a bunch of others and it
resonated with me because I've been a
gamer since I was 10 years old back when
we played Avalon Hill wargames on
tabletops and have gone through all the
evolutions in fact I recently had
created a phone based game which is out
for beta test right now so you mentioned
a dozen times so you must think that
sucks interest and saturation and games
particularly civilization is an
important insight into his personality
right I think it's telling the kinds of
games he gravitated to though I'm sure
he's not a stranger to shoot him ups he
really loved the game is where you built
a society and ran a society and you know
he plays board games - and risk was one
of his favorites he well into adulthood
and as you know the point of that games
to take over the world and when he first
started the Facebook which was what
Facebook was called when he launched it
at Harvard within a couple weeks
he was already gearing up to move it to
other campuses after he released it at
Harvard so the whole world of
universities became his risk board and
he went from one to another some of them
already had similar systems working but
he would take them over just like you
take over a country and risk where maybe
some pieces are already
they're from one of the opposing players
it was a good window into his mind yet I
actually noticed that when I was doing
my content prep for this call you
pointed out that the first college that
he went after after Harbor was Columbia
which seemed counterintuitive because it
had already had a similar service but a
game player might well say you know hey
guy want to attack that entranceway into
Australia in risk right rather than go
grab some cheap territory in Mongolia
because you know two things one I want
to crush an early opponent before they
can get bigger that's game thinking and
second in the meta game of business you
strengthen yourself by competition and
testing yourself against others and
learning faster than the other guy so I
would say you know suck probably did
internalize a lot of very useful lessons
from gaming I know I bet I mean I had
people ask me what are my influences in
my business career and I said war gaming
was certainly one of the top three or
four I was impressed by the fact you
know how often you you brought that back
and wove it into the storyline now
another question that really jumped out
at me again particularly as I was
reviewing my notes that Zuckerberg took
a consciously elitist educational
approach that seemed kind of contrary to
his own interests kind of demanded that
he go to Exeter and then Harvard he
always wanted to go to Harvard rather
than what we're seeing more natural
Stanford MIT Carnegie Mellon University
of Michigan University of Texas one of
the universities more well known for its
computer science department she did an
insights or you know motivational sense
of you know why this kid who clearly a
nerd and a geek would serve forcefully
pound the table for the extra hard route
rather than the you know public high
school MIT route for instance
right well the Exeter you know he had
heard about the they they have a great
computer program there and you know and
he he went as freshman sophomore years
of high school to the public high school
in Westchester County which wasn't a
terrible high school but he exhausted
all the opportunities he had for
learning about computers there his
mother wanted him to go to a closer
private school Horace Mann where he can
commute and she didn't want him to leave
the house his older sister was going off
actually to Harvard and she didn't want
to lose two kids
on the same year she wanted to have him
around for his high school years and he
said there I'm going to Exeter and he
said she said why don't I just at least
interview with Horace Mann and maybe
you'll like it
and he said all interview with him but
I'm going to Exeter I mean with Exeter
now the Harvard thing I think maybe
because his sister went there he knew
people he also was interested in some
non computer things he took a lot of
psychology courses and he was interested
in the classics and Latin heroes old
Gustus Caesar not Conqueror so I think I
said the best I can get to why he wanted
to go to Harvard he had a Harvard
pennant in his room and Exeter someone
called me which was interesting but
you're right it turns out that you can
make an argument that he might have been
happier MIT or Stanford
he was always building things and
Harvard wasn't really friendly to people
who were entrepreneurial then we're
close to Stanford or MIT and you know
other people there who you know had an
entrepreneurial bent and they felt big
the school didn't encourage them and you
know going you know Zuckerberg gone to a
spat with some other people you know in
terms of their companies and this has
sort of been documented not a hard
person accurately in this movie the
Harvard really didn't want to ending a
deal with that you know that wasn't
their DNA yeah that came up again and
again we'll get to that a little bit but
I'm I take a little sidebar here because
you mentioned it you know I did not have
any idea till I read your book that
Zuckerberg hero was Caesar Augustus
sir Octavian as he was known prior to
his ascent and that really struck me I
said you know there's something about
the Zuckerberg that reminds me of
Octavian right even looks sorta like
some of the younger statues of him I
wonder if he is consciously grooming
himself to be the Octavian or the
Augustus Caesar and people who don't
know the transition between the Republic
and the Empire Octavian was this very
unlikely character when Caesar Julius
Caesar was assassinated at the Senate by
Brutus and his friends as laid out
somewhat accurately I suppose in the
Shakespeare play Julius Caesar had been
publicized but not well known that
Caesar had recently made Octavian this
19 year old distant cousin his heir and
all the power brokers of the world
thought this little punk could be pushed
aside but guess what this little punk
was smarter more ruthless but quiet and
low-key than the rest of them and he
ended up killing them all off over time
and becoming the first emperor of the
Roman world for someone to choose
Octavian Augustus Caesar as their hero
is kind of a very interesting choice
yeah yeah that's a point where you know
he went I think was his honeymoon to
Rome and he dragged his wife
so all these sites that you know where
Divya went and you know the museum's
exhibits about this and she complained
that there were three people or any
movie you know G and Zuckerberg and
Octavius Caesar Augustus Caesar that's
amazing and I think that's that's
something worth considering comes you
know again in a historical context you
know Octavian or you know Gus the Caesar
could be thought as comparable to you
know a Napoleon or a Hitler or a Stalin
right only more successful than any of
them so I mean it's a very odd choice to
be you're here exactly he wasn't a warm
fuzzy guy yeah not at all I mean he was
a cold stone killer including you know
his own children his wife well I don't
think he killed him you know he exiled
them till they died basically today a
real real cold and tough guy
and conquered the world basically took
over the biggest Empire in world history
at that point it's the next point and
you alluded to it which was from the
very time he got to even in late high
school but in particular have time he
got to Harvard Zuckerberg was a
relentless small-scale web developer
being paid by other people and
entrepreneur trying all kinds of stuff
in a rather non Harvard ish kind of
fashion and that did put him a little
bit sideways with Harvard and as you
point out MIT or Stanford wouldn't have
cared you know I was I went to MIT in
the early 70s and the culture there was
man you had to do something pretty bad
on a computer to get into trouble and
you know the first time he came to the
attention I think of the authorities was
he creates something called face mash
essentially a juvenile take off on
hot-or-not
and it had a lot of the hacker ish
aspects you know scraping photos off the
official face site not concerned with
privacy or permissions etc but it was
within the spirit of the hacker ethos of
that time I'd say yeah it was but
Harvard didn't have much of a sense of
humor about it and I think it was a
combination of that he violated their
security rules you know by working his
way into the computers with the other
houses these residential houses that are
organized in in order to scrape the you
know the the databases get the pictures
but also it was a very politically
incorrect thing to do the the women's
groups at Harvard complained that they
were being objectified you know which
they were and so there was a lot of
pressure of Harvard not to ignore it and
of course the the the rules he violated
were free speech rules but were rules
about not breaking into computers and
and getting the information and the
lesson he learned from that was hey
don't do it again if I'm going to build
my site the is a community site and I'm
not going to steal the information from
Harvard I'm going to make people bring
their own that way there's no privacy
issue in terms of that because the
people
have provided it themselves about
themselves I got Ben to do it for me
in fact you mentioned the earliest days
of the Facebook there's a direct quote
from your book that the Facebook the
precursor to Facebook offered more
privacy protection than any other social
networks of its time so he did learn the
lesson even if it might have been
cynically the other thing I thought that
was interesting was you talked about the
hearing that he had before the deans etc
and he was given a slap on the wrist and
the actual charge was something like
improper social behavior I didn't harbor
desk kind of charge zuckerberg and has
social skills right then you you
mentioned again half a dozen times at
least the Zuckerberg trance really
apparently quite off-putting go on for
minutes and you quote one of people who
knew him really well as he falls into
and becomes the Eye of Sauron from Lord
of the Rings what are you willing to say
about Zuckerberg social skills and
social aspect right well obviously he's
evolved quite a lot from you know a 19
year old you know who was socially
challenged in her in the early years of
Facebook as a leader he would get very
nervous me addressing even his
relatively small team and in all hands
he has the have this habit of sometimes
you'd answer my question and he would
just stare here what happened the first
time I met him in 2006 and it's very
unnerving let me tell you and you wonder
whether there's something cognitive
going on there but it turns out he's
just processing things and he doesn't
left now but sometimes you can ask him a
question that he didn't expect there's
never an answer ready it'll give you
that look for a little while but nothing
like the like minutes long pause that
makes you go insane that he used to
happen he was a younger person with it
really minutes longer to just seem like
it maybe it seemed like it but sometimes
I think you know you would be
approaching that I mean oh really
way beyond what you're used to in terms
of one-to-one interaction local people
this how they went insane when that
happen people like Don Graham who was
the CEO of the Washington Post actually
was my boss at the time and Roger
McNamee it happened to a lot of people I
did I whenever viewed him once at the
end of 2006 at a conference and I asked
them a question and here is on stage and
they didn't answer the question for
minutes and people are getting nervous
in the audience or like nothing so I
think what's going on here what's going
on so it it really is something you
don't forget it's interesting I'm not
quite sure what to make of it like you I
have never experienced that with
somebody if I ask them a question and
they let's just say 60 seconds just sit
there and think about it before they
answer I suppose at one level it could
be a mark of respect that he takes your
question serious enough to think about
it for 60 seconds but on the other hand
it seems like you know missing the
normal social dialogue cues I think yeah
it's like he didn't want to play that
game in a way I mean he was willing you
know to take whatever he you know that
like that happened you know he because
it was Madadi hey've you know he wasn't
going to bow down to the the niceties of
social interaction he was he was he was
okay with himself being that way until
really he had the responsibilities of a
CEO and he became an adult and you don't
see that with him so much you know that
I once had that treatment from Bill
Gates so I once in 1996 I believe I was
doing a story the first story about the
browser wars and I went visited on him
in his office and you know gave him a
long complicated opening question about
the browser wars and he gave me that
silent treatment for a long time and you
know there was like this like dead space
in the room and you know I just finally
had minora question did he never did
answer we did he did I think he was more
conscious about doing it it was a more
of a tactic of saying you know fuck you
I'm not gonna answer this now and then
he then he did later he remember
you know at some level that seems a
little kind of lacking in social skills
on Zuckerberg at that time when he was
at Harvard but on the other hand
something that it struck me as showing
great social intelligence if Anna
Machiavellian Way was the way he played
the Harvard Crimson again and again he
got the Harvard Crimson to do a fair
amount of the work for him yeah yeah it
was like covering Zuckerberg for the
Crimson was like you know the way you
know like a publication covers Silicon
Valley he was a Silicon Valley of
Harvard single-handedly you know you
know can they would you know uh
obviously came to her attention after
that face matched issue but you know
they would write about his various
projects and when they wanted someone to
comment on something you know about you
know the web and products you know they
would like fall to him and and even
after he left Harvard obviously they
covered the Facebook really really
closely and you know we went out and
visited him in Palo Alto
masterful public relations for a you
know 17 or 18 year old kid I was
impressed I was never very good at
public relations and he was way better
than I ever was I'll say that when he
was a pup
also at Harvard again it was the subject
of that you know not entirely accurate
movie I forget what it was called was it
called the social network maybe
yeah the social yeah yeah you delve into
some degree the you know the story of
the Winklevoss twins Greenspan was
Zuckerberg over the line and ripping
them off it was at the hacker spirit of
sharing ideas and seeing who comes up
with something what's your take on that
if you don't mind yeah I didn't want to
dwell on that you know too much but I
had to look at it really you know
fashion you know do my own research and
and there's a couple points there one is
that the Winklevoss twins were not going
to create a product that took the world
by storm you know they were pretty
clueless about how they were doing
things you know they've been you know
like talking about the thing for a year
it wasn't an original idea
you know Friendster was already out lots
of campuses had their equivalent of a
Facebook so it wasn't a brilliant idea
there was something even on campus you
mentioned a guy named Greenspan he had
his own product
but when Zuckerberg did do which you
know was deceptive was he said that he
would help the Winklevoss twins and the
other guy for connect you is what they
were calling him originally Harvard
connection to code up their program it's
sort of telling that the the key person
and you know that these people wanted to
do you know was just someone they would
hire or you know and as a jobber you
know you know that they didn't really
have the skills to do that crucial stuff
themselves and the design really was
going to be everything in terms of the
success and for two months he said he
was working on it and he really didn't
work on it and he dragged his feet on it
and he actually shared with some other
people and it's the messaging that
that's is what he was doing that he was
slowing them down
but you know the two months difference
that it made for Connect you wouldn't
have made much difference anyway they
had someone working on it before they
didn't do anything they had someone
working on afterwards it didn't do
anything so as it turned out that
Zuckerberg messing him up for two months
was the best thing that ever happened to
them cuz I wound up getting millions and
millions of dollars in a settlement and
of course they gripe that they should
have gotten more but I think it was like
a total bonanza for them and it's just
absurd to say as they are saying and
their biographer keeps saying you know I
guess another book out about them you
know that Mark Zuckerberg had it not
been for Mark Zuckerberg that's
ridiculous I do give them some credit
for being on the Bitcoin thing early
yeah yeah that's that seems like a
reasonable take I mean it does strike me
having read it and get in your book that
Zuckerberg was a little more duplicity
than one might like however the
probability of Winklevoss twins and
friends actually having created Facebook
quickly when you look at all the odd
luck and right place right time that
Facebook had with exactly the right
product idea seems unlikely yeah there's
an extraordinary number of people who
have been made like super rich certainly
simply by being around they're involved
with Mark Zuckerberg who like spend a
lot of their time complaining about it
that's what I found yeah you know that's
interesting that's my next question was
going to be people who were round very
tightly with him early very tight and
more tightly than anybody and what's
their take on Zack Hughes and Moskovitz
did you get a chance to talk to those
guys Dustin Moskovitz who is probably
the closest lieutenant in the early days
of Facebook and he turned out to be a
really a great executive a CTO of for
Facebook in the early days when he left
he has never been on the record as
thrashing Facebook there is probably
clues that he's not thrilled of the
direction the Facebook took but you know
he has a I there's a possibility and I
don't know because I actually didn't
talk that to Dustin he you know can I
think it's telling the hidden talk
to me maybe because he didn't want to
have to express what he thought of
Facebook or maybe he just didn't want to
talk to me but maybe he feels this guy
made me one of the richest people in the
world is being ridiculous for me to
trash him other people didn't have that
problem Chris Hughes you know walks away
with hundreds of millions of dollars and
has no problem you know for for
basically doing something nothing dumb
extraordinary at all you know what he
brought to Facebook he was basically
answered the phone and for press stuff
and and you know can did some other
things which you know weren't
extraordinary but um you you know he was
lucky enough to be involved as a founder
and now he's going around you know
saying the Facebook should be broken up
I don't know I mean you know you're
allowed to express your opinion but it
doesn't seem like a great karma thing to
do it's not giving back the money that's
the thing if he said you know what
here's about five hundred million
dollars I'm gonna give it all to charity
I'm gonna live like I would live
otherwise right I'm gonna give up this
my nice house in Greenwich Village the
nice house in upstate New York and you
know although other money I have and you
know because it's dirty money is blood
money they don't say that right and you
know so I I think that the it doesn't
seem kind to me I don't know yeah
although I will didn't notice that there
weren't too many people that stuck with
Zach or that he stuck with her for very
long I mean he went through cleaning
house yeah there are there some he went
through cleaning house after Yahoo tried
to buy Facebook for a billion dollars
and the Zuckerberg didn't want to do
that Zuckerberg eventually kept Facebook
as we know but he made a point of making
sure that a lot of people around him who
were telling him sell sell sell were
gone after that yeah that's the Octavian
in him right you're either with me or
you're not and that's also I have to say
that was a tremendously huge octavian
move was to turn down a billion dollars
when it wasn't at all clear that your
business was worth a billion but he saw
it and he said that if you know he I
think he saw that if he could
stick his ground and just relentlessly
focus and oh by the way have a night of
Long Knives and take out these people
that didn't agree he had its fair chance
to build something much more significant
I mean that's a really big kind of world
historical move and how old was he at
that time 23 maybe if that yeah no no it
was you know yeah 22 yeah it's amazing
got to give him some octavian points
there for that move I sure as shit
wouldn't my own entrepreneurial career
was quite the opposite I built him to
sell three to five years put the money
in the bank on to the next one's a very
different game what's interesting is he
took those lessons the way he felt and
used it to get founders of other
promising applications you know I'm
talking about what's up and Instagram
and you know these are founders that
didn't want to sell their operation and
he got them to sell to him so you know
these are people who want the same way
he did but he understood how to get
under their skin and to make them make
the concession but he refused to make it
on the other hand he just overpaid so
crazily I'm like he paid 19 percent of
the capital value of Facebook for
whatsapp and it still hasn't made any
money right or very little I'll tell you
there if you put up what's up for sale
for twenty billion dollars now you know
there would be a lot of takers and if
you put it up what's up for sale for a
hundred billion dollars you know the you
know you I mean if it went public you
know you could argue you can get a
hundred billion dollars if it's a one of
the most successful social applications
in the world so that even at that level
it's worth a lot it's worth a lot more
to Facebook because they don't think
appeal against it exactly that's why
they actually did it right to basically
co-op competition and then oculus the
other case again two billion dollars for
very early impressive but not clear what
the market was really hasn't turned into
a hell of a lot he did it by brute force
and I would say the essentially
anti-competitive nature of
zap made a lot of sense but I can't
fault the founders of whatsapp at all
for turning down when you're a 40-person
company being paid you know 20 billion
dollars is a ridiculous so he's just
overwhelmed them nobody offered
Zuckerberg a payout quite like that he
probably would have taken it maybe not
but he oh he got Instagram for a billion
dollars which was what the offer was for
him from Yahoo so that's a good example
that's more equivalent he found founders
who weren't as Octavian as he was
essentially yeah you know and the big
thing that he was gonna concede to them
was independence you know they could
still run it like they owned it which
they did for a while until he decided
that those days were over and you know
I'm in charge now and Instagram now
exists will serve Facebook but what you
would expect eventually right that's the
nature of selling your company exactly
so the founders of both what's up and
Instagram had to come to terms that as
unhappy as they were that deal was
sealed when they sign the contract
that's why whenever I sold my companies
I negotiated my exit I had no desire to
continue to run the companies for longer
than necessary the reality is if
somebody else owns it you've lost the
ability to do what you want to do let's
go back a little bit to the late early
Zuckerberg which I found again very
interesting and again very much in the
spirit of the 1984 hacker ethos I wish
it was the chapter you called Casa
Facebook where they a whole bunch of
them were living in a house and you know
some of that I think was in that that
movie also and I loved you know
character the guy who just keeps showing
up in the more interesting place as
Shawn Parker and his insight that it was
the fact that Facebook was based on real
names only unlike the other social media
platforms that made it so important how
formative do you think that Casa
Facebook and Shawn Parker and and that
epoch was in making Zuckerberg who is
well I think what happened in that
period this is you know a few months
after the Facebook started the team
moved the Silicon Valley for the summer
ostensibly and you know they ran into
Sean Parker who had a lot of experience
even though was a only a few years older
than them
in in the valley had been a mobster and
he started a company called Plaxo which
he sort of screwed out of by the VC
funders em then they got in touch
through Parker with people like Reed
Hoffman and more thinkest so immediately
they were talking to the most important
people in Silicon Valley who understood
social networking and and they
understood the ecosystem how do I get in
touch with funders and very quickly by
the end of that summer they had funding
a you know from Peter Thiel you know
millions of dollars and in Hoffman and
Pincus put their own money in so that
was important but just as important was
Zuckerberg being exposed to that growth
mentality of Silicon Valley you know
Zuckerberg as we talked about earlier
was very big on expansion and growth but
he really saw how not gonna be possible
by really getting in touch with the
people who were the cutting edge of
growth hacking in in in the valley and
and he began to think about what
Facebook could be beyond a campus
network and I actually got hold of his
secret notebook where he was writing his
visions for Facebook in 2006 of how to
change it from a campus network to
something where everyone in the world
would have it so I think those years and
those connections were very formative
for him yeah I love this notebook and
your references to it do you actually
have his notebook I don't have the
physical notebook but I have some he
destroyed it but I I have the copies of
the pages which he doesn't have anymore
so you know I I showed it to him
eventually and he couldn't believe it
cuz he's well I'm looking at this I
don't have it I'm sorry I got rid of it
interesting cuz I actually have a note
board for one of my ventures it's one of
my prized possessions it's one of those
French little paper books with the
flexible covers what do you call them I
forget but anyway the beautiful little
note book and it's absolutely full of
stuff and I still go back and look at it
and go holy moly if I had the notebook
for Facebook from 2006 it would be one
of my prized possessions did he ever ask
you for the copy I should actually just
I should send you my promise I said to
me after the book game what I think I
would all do that yeah if I was him I
would find that to be a prized
possession let's go back to talking
about the insight that Shawn Parker had
about real names I was a little late to
the day on Facebook I think I joined in
2009 and previously I had skipped
Friendster but I had yeah little
investment my myspace account and
what-have-you and that was my reaction
also well when I took a look at Facebook
in 2009 I go wow this could be a much
better ecosystem because these guys have
figured out how to have a reasonably
strong real name ID and not you know the
crazed myspace thing with all anonymity
that was ugly and too easily to be
spammable etc I still believe to this
day that the thing that let Facebook win
at around that time 2008-2009 was that
the choice of real name identity was
really different than what most people
do look at reddit for instance again
similar time frame you know reddit has
always been rigorously anonymous if you
want to be Twitter the same but real
names make a big difference you know you
and I are both on the well and the well
was famous from the very beginning no
matter how big a celebrity you are you
shall use your real name and didn't
allow the well to conquer the world but
it did make for a very much better
ecosystem than systems built around
confidentiality how central do you think
real names is to the Zuckerberg vision I
think is important I think that one
reason why there have a lot of problems
now is they have the scale the Facebook
operates it's tough to police that to
make sure that
everyone who is who they say they are
there's like five Facebook amidst the
five percent of the accounts are bogus
accounts and they report in eye popping
numbers of attempts to create fake
accounts billions of you know every
quarter so you know kind of course a lot
of those are basically just bought
trying to you know open one account
after another but uh even 5% can cause a
lot of problems I I think it is
important to know that when someone yeah
if your identity is if it's who you are
you're going to be generally more
careful about what you post then you're
gonna be answerable to it when you break
the rules Facebook I think could be
tougher about enforcing that but I think
that they don't want to have their
numbers go down if they're too tough
they don't want it anyone turned away as
a false positive fakery
so that 5% which is you know probably
the minimum is a big problem for them
because it it's a better community for
all if everyone you know like knows who
they are
right just like if you know uh people
walked around and you couldn't tell who
they were they might be less polite it's
like I said if you're in a small town
you know who everyone is you know
there's a big incentive to behave better
because it's your reputation absolutely
and I do find it interesting that
despite the fact the you know
essentially utterly immense financial
resources that Facebook has it has not
tried to upgrade the quality of its real
name identity and in fact this I found
very curious they've essentially as I
understand it closed off their program
of the equivalent of Twitter's blue
check because you know there is an
argument that you don't want to close
the front door with too rigorous of
screening and I think Zuckerberg has
said elsewhere that he's particularly
concerned about the third world where
people don't necessarily have firm
documentary identity you know in the
United States easy enough have people
you know send a picture of their drivers
license or their you know other
government ID but in you know Uganda
that's not going to work so well but
however you could have
upgraded ID yeah also to be fair
Facebook ran into a lot of problems of
people who had good reason not to use
their real identities you know people
who you know might have you know had
sexual identity that they didn't want to
share with everyone so that was a real
dilemma for them and they decided since
facebook was so important to people they
wouldn't deny people access to that so
you know and in that case they had a
genuine dilemma yeah there would be good
if they seems to me it'd be really good
to me if they would go and offer two or
three levels of augmented identity right
maybe charge for it charge ten bucks to
go through the yeah the know your
customer level or you could you could
then make your own setting to say I only
want to interact with people who have
been vetted sort of like the you know
trust the traveler program or something
like that yeah I mean if it seems like a
natural thing to do but probably they're
computer simulations show that it would
you know ones wouldn't wouldn't help
growth I'll tell you that
exactly and that's all it's about and
what's it by next topic the next kind of
strikingly influential individual that
Zuck hooked up with was Peter teal and
you tell the story that one of teals
guys I think it was her friend of teals
or something
focused on the unbelievably amazing and
rapidly growing engagement numbers of
Facebook even in those early days and
that's what hooked teal to be the first
significant investor and as we talked
about earlier worshiping engagement in
some sense became the dark hole into
which facebook has fallen or did fall
any thoughts on Zuckerberg and teal well
teal you know was the first big investor
and he has been a board member you know
for the Facebook's history and I think
as a trusted advisor to Zuckerberg and
you know he is long advocated the
companies do best when they have a
monopoly when a corner of the market
send that map thinking if it didn't
influence Zuckerberg it certainly syncs
with the way Facebook is behaved over
the years
yeah and I will say I know teal just a
little bit and I would say he's another
really ruthless dude you know
interesting guy interesting guy I mean
back you know back when and there's
early days of Facebook
tl was one of those people that he had a
PR person who would call you all the
time and say Peters available to comment
on this Peter's available to comment on
that
no he won't talk to journalists but um
back then he was eager to get his name
out one of the things that you call out
of course its famous about Facebook it's
move fast and break things but you also
dig into the fact that it's not just an
attitude to move fast and break things
but also that they were one of the early
companies that heavily invested in what
we now call DevOps where you don't take
months to bring out a feature it takes
hours to push a feature into production
if it doesn't work you pull it back
right where did that ethos come from is
that Zuckerberg himself was that
Moskovitz some kind of group think that
realized the strategic importance of
DevOps and very rapid pushing of
features out yeah we touched them out
earlier I mean I was a huge advantage
for Facebook in in the early days
did you know they understood you know
coming from Zuckerberg is used to the
tools and and he taught those tools the
Moskovitz who really wasn't you know
that much of a coder when he started age
is really want to become part of it and
he learned it very quickly then this is
something people do people didn't
realize this people grew up in the PC
age in the Microsoft way of looking at
things that you would do an upgrade like
every year or every couple years and you
can do you know sort of Inc from mental
you know thought upgrades you know like
every few months they didn't realize
that it was possible to do upgrades
several times a day and you could push
stuff out and the advantages if
something didn't work if there was a bug
you could just have the new version
ready that would refresh the next time
people you know open the browser yeah
and this is a great advantage of not
being bound by the previous paradigm
that Facebook took advantage of then
enable it to move much quicker than
everyone else
yeah and I will say my own business
theory when I was a entrepreneur was I
ripped off Hunter Thompson faster and
faster till the thrill of speed exceeds
the fear of death right and it's a huge
competitive advantage and they took it
to the next level course Google had also
moved to that as we know nothing is
closed when Google started Google was
not in that paradigm you know Google
used to do like updated surgeons and
every month when in the early days and
that didn't have to speed it up till
I've got the AOL deal in 2002 I think
because you know yo L demanded that they
upgrade it more frequently and then of
course they also nowadays nobody sees
the same Google right they have a
hundred different tasks going on
simultaneously is very very impressive
but you're right the Facebook probably
got there with brute force and as a deep
philosophical foundation before anybody
else and that's been very important yeah
on the other hand it's an attitude that
isn't necessarily very complimentary to
you know this heightened sense of social
responsibility that we talked about at
the beginning and you know that's that's
gonna be a real tension a company whose
DNA is move fast and break things so I
think they've actually changed that to
something else so now being a
responsible adult where maybe that's not
the greatest idea any sense on what
degree that tension between the original
ethos and this new awareness post 2016
of social responsibility is playing out
yeah well the the move fast and break
things originally was meant to talk
about we were just talking about the
idea that you could crash the code you
know you take this thing down but that's
okay because you know in an hour we'll
have a new version and it was a badge of
honor among new engineers at Facebook to
actually take the system down and that
became a metaphor for moving fast in a
product sense as opposed to a code sense
and so you could have a product that
broke privacy and then fix it later
and you know you could break Myanmar and
fix it later and that Matt and that's
where they got into trouble and now you
know uh just like they changed their
motto they're trying to say well we now
understand that probably it's a good
idea to think about the consequences of
the products we put out before we put
them out so we're now looking to be
proactive about what impact our products
could have on society that gives me a
good transition point to a next
interesting topic which is the
relationship between Sheryl Sandberg and
Jacques in some ways may be a precursor
was the fairly prescient realization by
Pierre Omidyar that he needed a lot of
help and brought in Meg Whitman at a
very early stage and you know though I
do think the the partnership there was
more one-sided toward Meg rather than
Pierre over time but it's a some degree
suck as you point out also said here's a
big round circle around shit I don't
want to be dealed with and Sheryl you
deal with it I'll confess my own
business career I did the same though
not at the levels up that I would always
hire a very strong CFO and I joke with
them hey your job is to be the king of
ash and trash anything I don't want to
deal with you get but I did not go
anywhere near as far as sucked it in in
pushing things over to to Cheryl what
she did could you talk a little bit
about how that to the green you were
able to ascertain how that relationship
started how its matured and where it's
at today
yeah I talked about them both
considerably about this you know about
the decision you know and they he
brought in Sandberg you know he was a
fantastic executive at Google and just a
brilliant business person so she did
have role as a show or reminded me when
we talked the you know that she had a
company-wide role in helping with the
culture of Facebook moving in little off
the dorm-room culture and being you know
friendlier to women in particular and
and being a little more socially
conscious in terms of place to work but
they actually divided up the company and
and as just as you said there were
things that Zuckerberg wasn't so
interested in he was interested in
engineering and product and that was
what was going to be what where he spent
his time and the rest of its sales
lobbying in Washington HR while content
moderation that went over to the Sheryl
side and that was her world that she
would run and and there was a
disincentive for her to flag problems in
her world to him she felt that she
should be dealing with them herself but
there are some problems that are so
important that the CEO really needs a
deal with it the company doesn't really
take it seriously until they see the
signal that wait a minute this see this
is a CEO level issue and that's some
things like what happened in the 2016
election the this stuff was in Cheryl's
world and it was not dealt with from a
CEO level and it really should have been
is because it turns out these are the
things that had terrible impact on the
company over the next few years as it
also turns out of course when you do
that division you miss the overlap which
is as we talked about earlier if you
build a product which was Zuckerberg
domain that uses machine learning to
identify cognitively button-pushing
content that's gonna have policy
implications right so you can't quite
firewall those two things out and
perhaps that conversation didn't happen
if they firewall to two divisions too
strongly right right yeah I mean it
wasn't like there was no
but like the AI people reported a Zuka
burg and they gave the tools to the data
people who work for assembler so it was
and we sold from Sandberg's organization
so there was this disconnect between
them and another thing that was in wound
up in Cheryl's world was security the
chief security officer reported to the
general council who reported to the
policy person who reported to Sheryl
Sandberg well wait a minute your chief
security officer the person with the C
and his title you know how many steps is
away not from the CEO Oh Sheryl and then
he's a step farther even farther away a
big gap between him and the CEO you know
can I was shocked to find that the chief
security officer never had a one-on-one
with Mark Zuckerberg you imagine that
I'd remember reading that in your book
and I was utterly shocked you know and I
was CEO of network solutions and then
later division president for Vera signs
digital certificate division security
was absolutely at the top of my list
right and while we didn't call them
chief security officers in those days
with the C titles were no longer or
nowhere near as promiscuous as they are
these days Zuckerberg cut back on C
recent years you didn't want any other
C's well I think that's a damn good
thing but I would certainly have a
direct report who would keep me under li
apprised of security because security is
the life and death of a data-driven
network company and Zuckerberg should
have understood that where do you sense
the Zuckerberg Sandberg relationship is
these days is anything changed have they
learned lessons how have they evolved in
response to this much different more
adversarial public environment well I
think there were tensions you know as
these things when it played out over the
past few years but there's sort of bound
together at this point I feel the I've
had some super interesting interviews
with Sandberg in the light a lot of
stages of my book and one of them I said
because Sandberg really prepare
is meticulously for every interaction
that she has that's the kind of person
she is and you know and I wanted to kind
of get past the prep documents and
really get down to the - there's a level
of candor which doesn't often throw
doubt colliders so I said I need two
hours where you Cheryl
which isn't heard of in Cheryl
scheduling but she finally did give me
those two hours and in the second hour
you know we had an extraordinary
exchange where she you know all her
frustrations poured out about what had
happened over there over the past few
years and it was clear to me you know
that she is a believer in Facebook
she's a very exacting person she could
be tough on her subordinates but she's
toughest on herself and she's in great
pain then she didn't perform in every
aspect as well and she could of doing
this crisis you know leading up to the
crisis she could it should have been a
more on top of things that prevent stuff
from happening so this was painful there
and it is part of this very human story
of Facebook and that's really what I
tried to do in this book is tell that
story of you know without demonizing
people but you know showing them is the
flawed human beings they are who can do
things something extraordinary like
building this company that has now three
billion people using its products in the
world as a huge percentage of the
world's population yet as well as it did
a lot of good it caused a lot of harm
and they're grappling with that and and
and then you know they throw men at a
lot of ill-will so how did that happen
it's sort of a tragic story in a sense
and you know god I hope people could
like read this like the story it is and
a very important story because Facebook
is so important to us and Instagram and
Facebook and we scream what's up you
know they're all important oculus might
be important one day so it is you behind
the scenes and this rich story of you
know attaining Heights and paying a
price for ambition you know can may be
too much ambition yeah indeed I would
strongly recommend this book to my
because as Steven says it's a story it
draws you in
it's full of you know human conflict
human foibles the profiles of Sheryl
Sandberg someone I probably knew a lot
less about than Zuckerberg we're very
illuminating so double thumbs up on
Stephens book Facebook one last thing
here before we go what do you see as
next in the evolution of Facebook I mean
you've gotten your head into this more
deeply than anybody you have you know 40
years experience in the evolution of the
techno sphere what do you think is next
for Facebook as a company well as I
started talking about this book you know
I had a book tour cut short by this
pandemic and it's been very interesting
to see the impact of that on Facebook
weirdly I mean I don't want to say you
know obviously it's a terrible thing to
benefit it was something that's caused
like death and financial hardship on so
many people but people have turned to
Facebook in a way they have in in recent
years some people who very
self-consciously deleted Facebook cuz
they thought it was toxic and no good
for the world are now coming back
because it it turns out to be one of the
more effective tools for being in touch
with people and what I've been sort of
pressing Zuckerberg to tell us is is
this going to change maybe the way he
sees Facebook the way go back to a maybe
it was before he was encouraging this
morality where it would be used more to
keep in touch with people through more
benign uses and Facebook itself has been
more aggressive about fact-checking
content policing content and actually
pushing content out to people about this
virus so it's maybe an opportunity for
Facebook just like world war ii was an
opportunity for the u.s. to get out of
the depression
maybe this crisis as a way for facebook
to get past its reputational tailspin
which nothing had had been able to do
before this had had any effectiveness
interesting that's let's hope so I will
say I found and you know I've never been
a huge basher of Facebook even though I
will say over the years my engagement
with public Facebook or open facebook
has declined and but I do find Facebook
very useful in its groups right
and during this Cove in nineteen
pandemic some of the groups I've been a
member of I would say have done the best
sense-making on what's really going on
and what to expect of any place I've
seen better than the professional media
I know Zuckerberg and you mentioned it
in the book does have great hopes for
groups as a way to you know move move
Facebook to the next level will be
interesting to see if this Koba 19
provides a catalyst for that you know
you know Mark Zuckerberg would be very
happy to hear you say that because as
you mentioned you know he made a special
focus the year after the election to
tell these meaningful groups as he calls
them you know the the groups that people
join that give them valuable information
or you know speak to important part of
their identity you know could not point
it like a hundred million people which
is a like a blip in Facebook we're all
in those groups and he wanted a billion
people to be on those those groups and
maybe that number is rising considerably
now yeah I would say 90 percent
literally 90% of my usage of Facebook is
in you know a handful maybe a dozen
groups that I belong to and the quality
of this course for a well moderated
group is just remarkably better than it
is on the open Facebook and finally
Facebook has been investing in tools for
group admins which make it a lot better
I'd like to see him do more of that but
for many years the toolkit was pretty
static well Steven I want to thank you
for an incredibly insightful discussion
here about your book and again like to
encourage my readers who are interested
in Facebook to check it out a book well
worth reading time well-spent you know
thanks I'm buy it from your independent
bookstore they really hurt indeed thank
you very much and we're gonna wrap
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com